Chris: Software developers need to use
good coding principles and practices.
Good coding practices are important in programming
and are achieved by using a variety of principles,
which may initially seem tedious and time
consuming but may be advantageous long term.
Leah: Cluttered code can cause problems
when it is further extended, and when the
same code needs to be worked on by a wider
‘Developer team’, so this is one of the reasons
why there are rules for writing good code.
Let’s take a look at some of the
most common principles used in
programming and software development:
Chris: The KISS Principle
The KISS Principle is a term that is widely used
in a variety of different industries so let’s look
at what it means especially in relation to coding.
KISS is an acronym for a design principle
noted by the US Navy in 1960 and it stands
for ‘Keep it Simple and Straightforward’
and covers many different areas of design
including engineering and programming.
There are other variations of this including ‘keep
it short and simple’ and ‘keep it simple, stupid’.
Whatever way it is used it means the same thing.
Leah: ‘Keep it simple stupid’ or
even ‘keep it short simple’ are
most commonly used in programming.
By keeping the programming simple, service
and maintenance are much easier and there
are no hard and fast rules regarding the
implementation of code, only that it should
be simple and therefore easily modified.
There are a number of ways to keep
your code simple these could include:
Chris: variables – keep the scope as small as
possible, don’t reuse variables, declare the
variables you are using and name them properly.
Functions – keep as small as possible and ‘pure’
DRY – write ‘Don’t Repeat Yourself’ code
YAGNI – Use the ‘You Aren’t Gonna Need
It’ principle – in other words write
the least amount of code that you need
SOLID – use the SOLID principle.
Leah: There are many reasons for
implementing the KISS philosophy.
It may prevent you from wasting time and
effort developing complicated protocols
which take a long time to write.
However, the primary benefits, are for
those that may use the software afterwards.
This could include both other
programmers and customers who want
a product which is simple to use.
SOLID principles
Chris: In programming S O L I D is a mnemonic
acronym used for the five design principles
which are intended to make programs more
‘understandable’, ‘flexible’ and ‘maintainable’.
Let’s look at what these are.
S - The Single Responsibility Principle
Leah: The Single Responsibility Principle
[SRP] states that every class or method
is responsible for one single, separate
part of a program’s functionality.
In other words each class should
only have one reason to change.
Good practice of SRP will prevent
side-effects from future changes and
make software easier to implement.
Chris: O – Open / Closed Principle
Software entities should be open for
extension but closed for modification.
In other words you should be able to add new
functionality without changing the existing code.
So, for example with OCP, if you change one class
there is no need to change all related classes.
Leah: L – Liskov Substitution Principle
Properties of one original class should
be replaceable with objects built
from classes adapted from the original
without breaking the application.
For example, if you had a ‘superclass’
with its own ‘subclasses’, with LSP you can
change the objects of the ‘subclass’ without
affecting its associated ‘superclass’.
Chris: I – Interface Segregation Principle
No client should be forced to
depend on methods they do not use.
With ISP it is good practice to have
several client specific interfaces rather
than one large general-purpose interface.
This reduces the side effects that could
occur from using a larger interface
as the developers would be focused on
their own client specific interface.
Leah: D – Dependency Inversion Principle
Abstraction should be used to decouple
high-level and low-level modules from each other.
This way high-level modules which sustain
complex systems, are not affected by low-level
modules which provide utility features.
High and low level modules should depend on
abstractions which do not depend on details.
This means that if the details change,
they do not affect the abstraction.
Abstraction is one of the key principles of
object-oriented programming where the programmer
hides all but the relevant data about an object
to reduce its complexity and increase efficiency.